Joel Ferreira Barbosa

Haarlem, The Netherlands | Phone: +30 06 10305468 | joelbarbosa.ads@gmail.com | https://github.com/joelbarbosa | http://linkedin.com/in/joel-barbosa

Summary

Software Engineer at ING Bank with **8 years of experience**. Experienced with all stages of a software cycle providing solutions in architecture, development and maintenance of web and mobile applications. I like to study and apply the best practices, Data Structure, Clean Code, Tests, Design Patterns and always thinking in the tradeoffs I have made in my applications.

Experience

Software Engineer

June 2019 - Current

ING Bank - Amsterdam, Netherlands

- Providing mobile solutions in the FrontEnd Engineer Team, for IOs and Android with JavaScript, React, React Native, Java, Kotlin and Swift.
- Here I am working at the investment team, develop new solutions in the Beleggen app (ING Investing).
- With around 60k+ users our app grows fast with most modern pipeline, to guarantee the quality I am involved with TDD, Unit Tests, UI
 Tests, Pair Program and Code Review.
- As we are a bank and the security comes first. I am involved with a lot of Native Code in IOs and Android, working for performance the Bridges that communicate with JavaScript.
- IOs: https://apps.apple.com/nl/app/ing-beleggen/id1231921275
- Android: https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.ing.investment

Most Important Environment: JavaScript, React, React Native, Git, Jest, TDD, Java, Kotlin, Swift, Flow for Type, Mobx...

Full-Stack Developer

March 2015 to Current - 4 years

Grupo Marquise - Fortaleza, CE Brazil

- Architected, Design, Develop and Maintain all-new Web and Mobile applications to streamline the company's processes.
- The leader of Five Developers, with extra responsibilities such as developing the company's core solutions, training Juniors Developers
 and bringing new technologies to the health of the company.
- Web and Mobile applications thinking in Mobile First. Always concerned with scalability, clean code, code review and trying to apply the best practices from the Open Source Community.
- My latest Application is a React-Native app for the biggest mall in my company in the city of Fortaleza. The app is responsible for
 processing thousands of payments from the vendors. The Mobile app is being developed and maintained by me. I have to help the team
 in the Web FrontEnd with ReactJS and some AngularJS with Java in the Backend.
- http://www.grupomarquise.com.br/

Most Important Environment: JavaScript, Node JS, React, React Native, AngularJS, Redux, Redux-Saga, HTML, CSS, Express JS, Git, SVN, Jest, Mocha, TDD, Java, Spring MVC, Hibernate, Maven, JEE7, Spring Security, Oracle Database and MongoDB.

Software Engineer

September 2012 to February 2015 - 3 years

Grupo Edson Queiroz (Outsourced by IVIA) - Fortaleza, CE Brazil

- As part of the team, developer, and maintenance of the Financial System, Subscription system for magazines, Advertising management system for radio and television.
- Worked on developing new software architecture solutions.
- Migrated the desktop system to a web environment.
- http://verdesmares.com.br/

Environment: JavaScript, Java, JQuery, Bootstrap, HTML, CSS, JSF, Spring MVC, DWR, MyBatis, Hibernate, Primefaces, Oracle, JBoss, Wildfly and TomCat.

Software Engineer

August 2011 to February 2015 - 4 years

IVIA: A global IT services company – Fortaleza, CE Brazil

- Here I started my career as an Intern. I was contracted as a Web Developer.
- Customized components with JQuery and JavaScript.
- Migrated client systems to HTML5 and Mobile First.
- Developing systems with Java on the BackEnd, JQuery, and Bootstrap on FrontEnd.
- Systems with PHP using CodeIgniter MVC architecture.
- Documentations about the systems and its functionality.
- http://www.ivia.com.br/

Environment: JavaScript, Java, PHP, HTML, CSS, JSF, Spring, Hibernate, PostgreSQL, Oracle.

Education

System Analysis and Development

University Estácio de Sá - Fortaleza, Ceará - Brazil 2013 - 2018

Technologist in Telecommunications

Federal Institute of Ceará - Fortaleza, Ceará - Brazil

Languages

Portuguese, Brazil - Native

English – Bilingual proficiency